[Music]
hello everyone welcome back to the
channel in today's video we are on the
topic of Market structure we're talking
about swing structure and substructure
and how you can make sure you're using
the right kind of structure for the time
frames you're trading so on the chart
here I have an sample of Market
structure now structure is made up of
higher highs and higher lows or bearish
structure is made up of lower lows and
lower highs we determine the direction
of a trend by working out whether or not
the Market's making higher highs and
higher lows or lower highs and lower
lows the overall higher time frame
picture brings us the swing structure so
if we are on for example the daily chart
and we see the market moving up like
this we can see that we're at bullish
okay the trend is up so the swing
structure is therefore bullish it's
these larger impulsive moves in line
with the larger Trend now within the
swing structure the large upside moves
we do have these smaller corrective
moves okay we know that a trend is made
up of impulses and Corrections impulses
and Corrections and these corrective
moves are
substructure now within the substructure
we actually get smaller Trends going the
other way so inside of bullish swing
structure we will have bearish
substructure and inside of bearish swing
structure we have bullish substructure
now this is why it's important to know
which time frames you're trading and
which structure you should be using for
your trades because if you are a swing
Trader you obviously want to follow the
swing structure however if you are a day
trader you need to make sure that you're
not trying to trade with the larger
Trend when the lower time frame trend is
actually moving the other way so let's
actually go and have a look at this on
the chart an example of this so you can
see what I mean by this and you can
hopefully then begin picking up on using
the right structure and make sure that
you're not trading using the wrong time
frames so in this example we're going to
be looking at Euro USD on the daily
chart and I'm going to show you the
difference between the swing structure
and the sub structure now if we look at
Euro USD then from this point back in
mid June we can see that the Market's
actually been in a downtrend now we can
see the structure by actually marking
out the breaks of structure if we look
here we can clearly see we have multiple
bearish breaks of structure lower lows
and lower highs continually forming in
this market now this actually tells us
that the market is bearish and therefore
we may be looking for sells if we are
trading the daily time frame it's not
wrong to look for sells because we can
actually then follow the market
structure using you know higher time
frame zones now the mistake comes in
when you are trading the low time frames
maybe you're intraday trading or you're
trading the hourly the 30 minute and so
on and you're still trying to trade in
line with the bearish trend okay now if
we're at this point and we start looking
for shorts from where we are now this
could become a problem because the trend
on the lower time frames is substructure
so it may not be aligning with the
overall bearish picture so taking it
back to what we spoke about we can see
we have the impulse moves which are the
swing structure moves and we have the
corrective moves which are the
substructure moves now as we can see
right now after these large impulses we
are currently in a substructure move or
a corrective move okay so that means if
we are then trading the low time frames
so let's drop to the hourly for example
we need to make sure that we are trading
with the lower time frame Trend now we
can see here from looking at the hourly
chart that this is the low of the move
and from here we've actually had a
bullish Trend come in on that
substructure now if I just show you what
I mean here we can see that we had first
of all a break of structure from this
point and then we've had higher highs
and higher lows continually forming in
this market okay so what we would be
looking for is a break of structure
to the downside or a continuation to the
upside we need to make sure we're not
getting tied up in the wrong Trends as
we know we always want to trade with the
trend so that means if we're trading the
hourly time frame and the hourly time
frame is bullish then we trade bullish
okay if we're trading the daily and the
daily is barish we can trade it bearish
but only from the daily zones so looking
at this example on EUR USD then we can
see that the hourly trend is still
bullish and we do indeed have a supply
area up here which hasn't yet been
retested
so this is the movement where the
impulsive bearish move came in and what
that actually leaves us with is a little
bit of open space to the upside
here that we could look to trade through
now while the market continues to make
these higher highs and higher lows I
will therefore remain looking for buys
okay and then maybe we can start looking
for sells in line with the overall
higher Trend the swing structure Trend
but until then we must follow the
substructure because this is what's
going to bring us the Moves so if we
drop to some of the lower time frames
now and see how the market reacts we can
see that we do come down Wick through
but actually reject off that level so
what that tells us is that we are still
bullish and if we actually then go to
the lower time frames you're going to
see a trade that I took myself a couple
of weeks ago now as we can see the floor
held up quite nicely there we Wicked
just through but then we had a large
impulsive move and this brings us back
to substructure again now as you can see
from this the 5 minute substructure
within that hourly Trend was bearish and
from this point it's now broken and gone
back to bullish so at this point we
could begin looking for areas to buy
from because we can see here that the
trend is now moving bullish on the low
time frames which obviously aligns with
the hourly time frame as well and it's
at this point we could begin looking for
buys perhaps a little something like
this now this is actually a trade that I
took myself and as you'll see allowing
it to play out it did indeed work very
very nicely and it did go through the
target
level zooming out on that position we
can now look at the swing structure and
the substructure just so that you
understand exactly what it is I'm
talking about now if we see from this
point we have had an Impulse a
correction an impulse and a correction
so what that actually tells us is that
this is the swing structure and the
substructure are these smaller moves in
the opposite direction now as you can
see throughout the substructure we will
have selling opportunities and when the
structure then breaks on these lower
time frames that is when we then see the
corrective moves or the buying
opportunities in line with the
substructure when the swing structure
comes back into effect breaking the
structure of the
substructure we then move back down into
a impulsive move or a swing structure
move the larger time frame move to sell
through once again when that structure
then breaks we get the buying
opportunities in line with the
substructure so the key takeaway for
this video is to make sure you're always
trading with the right structure if
you're an intraday Trader you probably
want to be following that substructure
and if you are a swing Trader you should
be following the overall swing structure
of the movement and following the
overall larger impulsive movement here
we have the markup of the Swing
structure and the sub structure once
again just for you to recap I recommend
you take a note of this Mark it out uh
learn what this means and then actually
go and back test in the markets looking
at the substructure and the swing
structure learning to identify
substructure and swing structure and
making sure you are trading with the
right kind of structure based on the
time frames that you are trading I hope
you've enjoyed this video if you have
please drop a like and make sure you
subscribe so that you don't miss any
more future videos and drop a comment if
you have anything to say or any question
questions about the market structure I
put together a free mini course to
highlight the reasons why you're not
winning at trading it's going to show
you the top 10 reasons why you're losing
and how you can actually turn your
results around this course is a 13-part
video series it's entirely free to join
all you need to do is go to the link in
the description and sign up now I hope
you enjoy that course I hope you learn a
thing or two many students have given me
a lot of good feedback after going
through the course if you benefit from
it please do drop me a message just
giving me your feedback and i' love to
see how you progress your trading from
taking this course so remember the link
in the description is going to take you
to that free course hope you enjoy it
let me know how it goes